Inventory of the Dorsey-Coupland Papers 1840-1876, 1843-1865
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Dorsey-Coupland Papers, 1840-1876, 1843-1865.
Special Collections, College of William and Mary
Mss. 39.1 D73
413 items.
Correspondence, chiefly 1843-1865, between members of the Dorsey and Coupland families of Virginia.
Coupland Family,; Dorsey Family,; Dupuby Family,; Edmund Ruffin Family,; John R.Coupland,; Susan Henley Coupland,; Carter Coupland,; Juliana Ruffin Coupland Dorsey,; Jane S. Ruffin Dupuy,; Edmund Ruffin, Jr.
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
Presented: 413 items, 11/18/1927.
Scope and Content Information
This inventory contains correspondence, chiefly 1843-1865, of John R. Coupland of Williamsburg, Richmond and Petersburg, Virginia with his wife Susan Henley Coupland. Some letters were written to Susan Henley Coupland while she was in Williamsburg and he was in Richmond working in Second Auditor's Office of Confederate States of America War Department. Letters written by Carter Coupland while serving on Confederate steamers are also included.
This inventory also contains correspondence of Juliana Ruffin Coupland Dorsey with members of the Edmund Ruffin family and with her sister Jane S. Ruffin Dupuy and members of the Dupuy family. Includes letters written by Edmund Ruffin, Jr.; one letter, 20 June 1864, written by Edmund Ruffin (1794-1865) and letters containing references to him. Juliana Ruffin Copeland Dorsey and Jane S. Ruffin Dupuy were sisters of Edmund Ruffin (1794-1865).
Arrangement
Arrangement
After being organized into Series this collection is arranged chronologically by date.
Organization
This collection has been organized into three Series: 1. Letters, 2. Accounts, and 3. Miscellaneous Material.
Index Terms
Family Names:
Coupland family.; Depew family.; Dorsey family.; Ruffin family.
Persons:
Coupland, Carter, fl. 1833-1866.; Coupland, John R., fl. 1843-1866.; Coupland, Susan Henley, fl. 1843-1866.; Dorsey, Juliana Ruffin Coupland, b. 1806?; Dupuy, Jane S. Ruffin, b. 1800.; Ruffin, Edmund, 1794-1865.; Ruffin, Edmund, b. 1814.
Subjects:
Confederate States of America. War Dept.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865-- Naval operations--Confederate States.; Richmond (Va.)--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.
Components List
  Series 1: Letters
- Letters, 1840-1866, n.d., 174 items. (Box-folder 1:1-4)
  - Carter Coupland, Inglewood, to cousin Tiffy [Tariffa Cocke], Evergreen. Postmarked Meridian Springs, Massachusetts, 8 Feb[ruar]y [1840]., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Thanks his cousin for her letter and sends his love to her and the others at Evergreen; speaks of his trip to Jackson with his mother; met two boys his size that he played with; Brother George has a new spotted calf that allows him to saddle and bridle and lead around; knitted one stocking for his cat Rebecca Rosetta but tired of it and would not knit the other; Mr. Dorsey brought them oysters from Vicksburg; Mother has given him four hens but they have not laid yet; the weather is warming; Brother George will write Cousin Beck; sends love to Cousin Beck and Cousin Horatio and Little Betty; Mother and Brother George send their love; Brother John has gone visiting.
    Bears ALS from J[uliana] D[orsey], n.p., to Elizabeth R. Cocke, City Point, near Petersburg, Virginia. Mentions that they are all well; Mr. D[orsey] is improving; noticed a peach blossom and the potatoes are up but fears the frost will get to them; asks if Betty could send the blankets wrapped up in the bedding if it isn't too troublesome; sends love "to all friends"; B[?] returned from W[illia]m[s]b[urg] yesterday "much indisposed" to find Miss P[?] seriously ill; doubts if she will ever be much better; will write soon; Martha has chills, Jackson is gone, Tilla is the only remaining house servant. 1 p.
  - G.R. Coupland, Inglewood, to brother John R. Coupland, Elkridge Landing, Maryland Postmarked Meridian Springs, Massachusetts, 1 Jan[uary] 1841., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Hopes that he [JRC] is well since he was well in his last letter; describes Pensacola and the midshipmen on board the Warren who have been asking about him [JRC]; sends word of Midshipman Murry's coming in a schooner to get provisions and his killing of two Indians at Indian Key; convinced Uncle Harrison to write to Washington to get a Midshipmen's appointment for him [GRC]; describes Uncle Harrison's mishap with a rifle that nearly shot his hand off; has received two kids from Cousin Coupland; Mr. Fondren [?] sends his love and mentions he has made about 200 bales of hay; Rainy has made 50 bales at Mr. Fondren's [?] place; Brother Carter will write to Brother Johny [sic] soon; mentions his new colt and how her mane and tail were full of sheepburrs; soon he will be able to go hunting on her.
  - J[ohn] R. Coupland at [William and Mary] College, [Williamsburg, Virginia], to Susan E. Henley, n.p., 24 Feb[ruary] 1843., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Has fallen into despair because she has refused him; defines happiness as being with her; urges her to reconsider her decision.
  - Jno. [John] R. Coupland, Petersburg, [Virginia], to Susan E. Henley, Williamsburg, Virginia, 12 July [18]43., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Hopes it is not too soon after his departure from Williamsburg to write to her; describes his happiness and his love for her; becomes heartsick when he thinks of his journey southward in three months and having to put a great distance between them; is afraid she may fall victim to death or that she will change; has yet to tell Mother of their engagement; sends greetings to all who know of their engagement, which is to remain secret.
  - J[ohn] R. C[oupland], Evergreen, to Susan E. Henley, Williamsburg, Virginia. Postmarked Petersburg, Virginia, 20 Sept[ember] 1843., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Acknowledges he has been remiss in writing her; attempts to convince her that she is not disobeying her mother when she writes to him; reminds her of her promise to speak of their engagement to her brother; fears he may not be able to visit until the latter part of Nov[ember]; sends his love to her and to those to whom she can safely give it.
  - J[ohn] R. [Coupland], Mobile, [Alabama], to Susan E. Henley, Williamsburg, Virginia, 17 Nov[ember] 1843., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Has arrived safely in Mobile; troubles with stage contractors caused a delay in his arrival; has not decided on an occupation or a place to live; is currently residing with his cousin Mr. Minge [?], who left his wife in northern Alabama because of the fever still raging; the house is not ready to accommodate guests; reiterates his love for her; is frightened of yellow fever but will leave it to Providence.
  - J[ohn] R. C[oupland], Mobile, [Alabama], to Susan E. Henley, Williamsburg, Virginia, 20 April 1844., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Speaks of his love and devotion to her; chastises her for not writing; fears that he may not be able to see her until after the 4th of July due to his mother's having business in Mississippi until that time; gives his reason for not writing her; speaks of the balls and parties of Mobile that he would rather not be invited to; returns to the subject of his love for her.
  - John R. Coupland, Mobile, [Alabama], to Thomas H. Campbell, S.D. Whittle, H. Wiley, H. Woodis, and G.G. Thompson, committee, Williamsburg, Virginia, 25 June 1844. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Letter declining an invitation to a dinner to be given by the students of William and Mary College. See William and Mary Papers, Folder 16.
  - J[ohn R. Coupland], Petersburg, [Virginia], to Susan E. Henley, Williamsburg, Virginia, 14 August [18]46., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Opens his letter with no affectionate salutation because she asked "as you wrote, so do you expect me to write"; apologizes for his "dilatory conduct"; asks if she has "mentioned the matter to Ma'"; reiterates his love and devotion towards her; his having a chill and fever prevented him from traveling to Williamsburg; hopes she will not go to King and Queen [Ball] by then.
  - John [R. Coupland], White Sulphur Springs, [Virginia], to Susan E. Henley, Williamsburg, Virginia, 6 September 1846., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Is disappointed that "the crowd" from Petersburg has left and leaves him with little social opportunity; remembers fondly his stay in Williamsburg; declares his love for her; hopes to return to Williamsburg as soon as possible.
  - John R. C[oupland], White Sul[phur] Springs, [Virginia], to Susan E. Henley, Williamsburg, Virginia, 16 September [18]46., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Enjoys nothing in White Sulphur Springs without her; asks God to bless her for agreeing to link her destiny with his; believes this trip has been of "incalculable benefit" to him; will leave for Ohio either Saturday or Monday and be in Williamsburg as soon as possible.
  - John [R. Coupland], Milford Center, [Union County], Ohio, to Susan E. Henley, Williamsburg, Virginia, 14 Oct[ober] 1846., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Has heard no news from Williamsburg since he left White Sulphur Springs, [Virginia]; fears sickness or death has visited Williamsburg; worries that his friend Joseph Lewis is bed-ridden as he has not responded to his [JRC] letters; had expected to hear from her through his friends; warns her that if there are no letters for him in the next mail he will set out for Virginia immediately; worries that something, particularly sickness will prevent or delay his return; encourages reflection on the past as well as the present; reminds her they will be together soon; sends his love.
  - Frances [?], Williamsburg, Va, to her cousin John R. Coupland, Mobile, Alabama, 3 February [18]47., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Warns him that she [Susan E. Henley] is quite upset and has forbidden her [Frances] to write to him; shares news from Williamsburg; mentions that she [SEH] felt "slighted" and "treated with indifference" on his last trip to Williamsburg.
  - John R. C[oupland], Mobile, [Alabama], to his cousin F[rances], Feb[ruary] 1847., 6 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Finds himself in shock over her last letter; explains that she [Susan E. Henley] had promised to write him each time they were apart but never did; is angered that she [SEH] is upset that he "slighted" her by stopping writing when she never wrote; explains that he told her plainly at his last leaving that since she [SEH] will not write, she cannot expect to hear from him; will leave for Illinois and Ohio in four to six weeks; asks that she hurry a reply to him
  - John [R. Coupland], Mobile, [Alabama], to Susan E. Henley, Williamsburg, Virginia, 11 March 1847., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Has not heard from her or from Miss Frances [his cousin]; explains his reasoning for writing his last letter to Miss Frances; asks her to write to him.
  - Susan [E. Henley], Williamsburg, Virginia, to John R. Coupland, Mobile, Alabama, 24 March 1847., ACS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Gives him the choice of breaking their engagement or leaving the situation between them as it stands, depending on his desires.
  - Susan [E. Henley], Williamsburg, [Virginia], to John R. Coupland, Petersburg, Virginia, 17 June 1847., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Thanks him for his last letter; explains that their party went well; describes the party; gives news from Williamsburg; is glad he is over his chills and hopes he will not expose himself to the night air.
  - J[ohn] R. Coupland, Petersburg, [Virginia], to Susan E. Henley, Williamsburg, Virginia, 25 June [18]47., 5 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Cannot describe his pleasure at receiving a letter from her; echoes her wish that he could have been at her party with her; asks after Cousin Harriet and sends his love to her; worries about Miss Clarissa's health; discusses the love between two of their friends; promises he will be settled soon and then he can make her "the wife of my heart."
  - Edwin Shield, Williamsburg, [Virginia], to Susan E. Henley, [Williamsburg, Virginia], 18 July 1847., 1 p. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Thanks her for the kindness she extended to him.
  - John B. [?], Bethany, to his cousin Susan E. Henley, Williamsburg, James City County, Virginia, 27 July 1847., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Acknowledges the receipt of her letter; expects to leave for Williamsburg on 10 Aug. and arrive there 14 Aug.; will wait to share his news until he reaches Williamsburg.
  - John [R. Coupland], Baltimore, [Maryland], to Susan [E.] Henley, Williamsburg, Virginia, 19 Aug[ust] 1847., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Feels very alone in the midst of the crowds of Baltimore because she is not there also; describes his love for her; promises he will be kind to her once they are united; fears that his friend is dying and so will return immediately; has purchased a ring for her.
  - J[ohn] R. Coupland, Evergreen, to Susan [E.] Henley, Williamsburg, Virginia. Postmarked Petersburg, Virginia, 2 Sept[ember] 1847., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Had intended to go straight to Petersburg upon his departure from Williamsburg, but felt the tranquillity of Evergreen would be more suited to his state of sadness over leaving her; explains that he loves her because her "noble spirit has replied to mine"; promises to wear the ring she gave him; professes his deep love for her; sends his love to family and friends and asks for news.
  - Susan [E. Henley], Williamsburg, [Virginia], to [John R. Coupland], n.p., 15 September [18]47., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Rode out to the country the previous week to see Cousin Mary and Alice [?]; describes Mary's happiness as she will be married "October twelve months"; mentions Mr. Shields' visit the previous night; feels Mr. Shields "has completely thrown himself away"; urges him to visit Cousin John [?] on his way to Mobile if at all convenient as Cousin John is anxious to have him visit; send the love of all to him.
  - J[ohn] R. Coupland, Petersburg, Virginia, to Susan [E.] Henley, Williamsburg, Virginia, 21 Sept[ember] 1847., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Had expected to hear from her sooner; expresses his disappointment in the contents of her letter as being "better calculated to arouse a painful rather than a pleasant emotion"; surprised to hear of Miss Mary [?] and Conway [?]'s engagement; is sorry but he does not know of [?] Bolivar's whereabouts; asks if Harriet could send word when she hears from Bolivar; sends his regards to all; apologizes that the letter was a bit late but he was ill.
  - John [R. Coupland], Petersburg, [Virginia], to Susan [E.] Henley, Williamsburg, Virginia Postmarked 10 Oct[ober 1847], October 1847., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Has been sick since his departure from Williamsburg; looks forward eagerly to the time when they will be united; mentions that Mary Dupuy is honored by her [SEH] invitation and will respond immediately; has had a conversation with "Butch"[?] to explain why he [JRC] did not invite him to wait on him; sends love to all.
  - John [R. Coupland], Richmond, [Virginia], to Susan [E.] Henley, Williamsburg, Virginia, 27 Oct[ober] 1847., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Chastises her for not writing; wonders if she feels that she would rather be dead than marry him; is hurt that she remains silent this last week before their wedding; will invite some friends to their wedding.
  - John [R. Coupland], Richmond, [Virginia], to Susan [E.] Henley, Williamsburg, Virginia, Oct[ober] 1847., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Received her letter today; determines that the mail service is at fault for delaying her receipt of his last letter; decided not to travel to Richmond until he received her letter; tells her that his miniature should not be taken at this time as he is still recovering from his illness and he looks hollow and thin; promises to have a likeness made when he is well; sends his sympathy to James Christian, whose brother has died; discusses "the prospect of my old Alma Mater for the next two or three years" as "the course of the visitors has been indeed unfortunate"; mentions that if his letter is not all she expected, that his letters reflect the light of her own letters.
  - John [R. Coupland], n.p., to S[usan] E. Henley, n.p., 1847., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Is saddened by the prospect of leaving her; had an interview with Mrs. Henley which went satisfactorily, though Mrs. Henley cried at the prospect at her daughter's leaving her; believes that Mrs. Henley is satisfied with him as a husband for her daughter; asks her to be strong if their marriage necessitates their parting from her family.
  - J[uliana] D[orsey], Mobile, [Alabama], to her son John R. Coupland, Williamsburg, Virginia, 21 June 1848., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Hopes her letter finds him on his birthday, and hopes he is well and happy; mentions her heart's sadness after his departure, but now feels calm and satisfied; sends news of various acquaintances; wishes she could have joined him in visiting Virginia this summer; sends news of her activities; will send some hands to Mr. Morton for the summer to go to Pensacola with him as he will pay her 10 dollars round for men and boys; needs to find homes for the last two women and then she will be ready to move on the first of July; asks him to write to her.
  - J[uliana] D[orsey], n.p., to Mrs. John R. Coupland, Williamsburg, Virginia. Postmarked Mobile, Alabama, 13 July 1848., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Consoles her on the death of her grandmother by telling her that God's "mandate [had] gone forth and taken one, and another, and yet another, from your beloved circle, but only the aged, whose infirmities were almost intolerable, and whose preparation for death was made, and the smiling infant, innocent and pure, as God's hand and a Saviour's blood could make it, were called away" while the young stayed healthy; tells of the death and burial for Mr. Lewis and presents a eulogy for him; describes the beauty of her location on the Gulf Shore and wishes she could share it with her Virginia friends; speaks of her neighbors on the Gulf Shore and some of their social gatherings; sends greetings from their mutual acquaintances.
  - J[uliana] Dorsey, n.p., to her son John R. Coupland, Williamsburg, Virginia. Postmarked Mobile, Alabama, 17 Aug[ust] 1848., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Sends news of the death of Willis [?], who succumbed after suffering a series of chills resulting from catching some sleep on the Gallery immediately on the river while sitting up with a sick child; her son Carter was there when Willis died and is quite distressed; points out this warning of "the uncertainty of life"; gives religious reassurance as to the mercy of God after death; asks that Sue [Mrs. John R. Coupland] write to her [JD] son about "contracting bad habits" as the message "will sound sweeter from you"; advises them on the buying of a farm in Virginia as Mobile is more expensive; promises to help them in their search for a home.
  - Juliana Dorsey, n.p., to Mrs. John R. Coupland, Williamsburg, Virginia. Postmarked Mobile, Alabama, 2 Sept[embe]r 1848., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Assures her that the choice of her [JRC] home should rest wholly with her; tells her that they do not have the money to purchase a southern plantation, so they should look at settling on a small farm in Virginia; suggests also a small tract in Alabama to use for growing cotton; describes the area where she's living; the fever has hit in town again; shares news of friends and acquaintances that send their love; encloses some of her son George's hair, who passed away suddenly; mentions the tombstone she erected for him which cost $100; encloses the words engraved on the tombstone.
    Including AN from Juliana Dorsey, n.p., to Mrs. John R. Coupland, Williamsburg, Virginia, bearing the inscription of the tombstone of George Coupland. 1 p.
  - J[uliana] Dorsey, Mobile, [Alabama], to John [R. Coupland], n.p., 1 Nov[ember] 1848., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Informs him that their old friend Alfred Johns is willing to sell him some land on the Tensaw River; suggests that this land will suit him admirably; will purchase some nearby land for Carter [Coupland] as well; assures him that he can be settled within six weeks and then return for Sue [Mrs. John R. Coupland].
  - Robert Hughes, Galveston, Texas, to [Juliana Dorsey], n.p., 12 April 1851., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    Promises to send her the money he owes as soon as she informs him what the total amount is; has left behind all his office papers in Jackson and despairs of seeing them again; mentions also that he can repay her in the form of land in the future, but cannot do that at present as the land is held up in litigation.
  - Robert Hughes, Galveston, Texas, to [Juliana Dorsey], n.p., 15 June 1851., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    Apologizes for not sending the above letter, but was tied up in court until this time; reassures her that he will send payment when she informs him of the total amount owed; shares news of his family; asks if she will be in Mobile at least until the first of July, as he will visit her on his way to New Orleans if so.
  - Robert Hughes, Galveston, [Texas], to J[uliana] Dorsey, n.p., 10 October 1851., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    Strongly wishes to pay all those he owes money to, but cannot at this present time; has "scarcely received money enough to keep soul and body together" even though he has been employed in his profession since he arrived in Galveston three years before; informs her that he hopes to have some twenty or thirty thousand acres of land once the land litigation is over during the next winter; assures her that this land will go towards paying his debts at a reasonable price; informs her that she and Mrs. Martin will be the first of his creditors to be paid; hopes that she can come to Texas to visit and apologizes for not visiting her in Mobile; his son Archibald will be married in November, and will then join his father in the practice of law.
  - J[ohn] R. Coupland, Story Point, [Albermarle County, Virginia], to his mother Juliana Dorsey, Mobile, Alabama, 9 Feb[ruary] 1852., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    Is glad to hear that brother [Carter Coupland?] is doing so well; advises that she tell brother to set aside a bit of each month's wages "for money thought it may not be much always makes on feel independent"; shares news of his children; informs her that he is doing well this year; has raised a fine crop of corn and enough pork for his own consumption and some to sell; his wife Sue has made a small fortune with her pork; will slaughter one of her hogs today which is over 500 pounds, which will give him about $37.50.
  - W.J. Dupuy, Cottage Farm, to Sue [Mrs. John R. Coupland], n.p., 15 March 1853., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    Will cash the draft she sent for $1000 as soon as he gets to town; thanks her for the "kind and maternal care you have extended to my very dear Mollie during her late trying ordeal"; is anxious to see Mollie and the little fellow and will certainly have them with him by next summer; has only been able to fence in the field north of the road; two members of the church have died, even though the town has been "comparatively exempt from diseases this winter."
  - A. Sidney Robertson, Iberville, [Louisiana ], to [Juliana Dorsey], n.p., 18 January 1854., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)